The Beginning

In this chapter, which in the Hindi version began with a long invocation to the Hindu gods, Sita Ram tells of how he became a soldier, despite the opposition of his mother and the family priest, Pandit Duleep Ram. It was his mother's brother, Hanuman, who fired him with ideas of military glory. Hanuman was a native officer (Jemadar)[1] in the East India Company's Bengal Army, and Sita Ram mentions the gold beads worn by his uncle in uniform. These were a mark of distinction, native officers wearing one row of gold beads, and the sepoys three rows of white beads. Sita Ram refers to the East India Company as the Company Bahadur, meaning all-powerful. He also refers to it sometimes as the Sirkar, or government.

Sita Ram was a Brahmin, the highest Hindu caste, and he was therefore subject to the strictest religious observances which, as will be seen later, greatly complicated his life as a soldier. His father was a yeoman farmer of comfortable circumstances who lived in the village of Tilowee, in the Rae Bareli district of Oudh, in what is now the State of Uttar Pradesh (UP). Tilowee lies roughly midway between the cities of Lucknow and Allahabad in the very heart of Hindustan.

At the time of Sita Ram's birth, Oudh was an independent kingdom with its capital at Lucknow, and it was from Oudh that the East India Company recruited the bulk of its soldiers for the Bengal Army, and a lesser number for the Bombay Army. It had originally been a Mughal province, ruled by a Nawab appointed by the Emperor, but the Mughal empire was fast disintegrating by 1797, when Sita Ram was born, and viceroys of provinces had set themselves up as independent princes. The notorious misgovernment of Oudh led to its annexation in 1856 by the East India Company, resulting in much discontent among the soldiers enlisted from Oudh who lost under the Company the valued privileges they had formerly enjoyed in the civil courts when Oudh was independent. The annexation of Oudh by Lord Dalhousie was one of the contributory causes for the Indian Mutiny in 1857.

I was born in the village of Tilowee, in Oudh, in the year 1797. My father was a yeoman farmer, by name Gangadin Pande. He possessed about 150 acres of land which he cultivated himself. My family when I was young were in easy circumstances, and my father was considered a man of importance in our village. I was about six years old when I was placed under the care of our family priest, Duleep Ram, in whom my father and mother placed implicit confidence, and they never did anything of importance without his advice and consent. By him I was taught to write and read our own language; also a slight knowledge of figures was imparted to me. After I had acquired this I considered myself far superior in knowledge to all the other boys of my age whom I knew, and held up my head accordingly. All other castes were far below my notice. In fact I fancied myself more clever than my preceptor Duleep himself, and if it had not been for the high respect he was held in by my father, I should on some occasions have even dared to tell him so. Until I was seventeen years of age I attended my father in the management of his land, and was entrusted to give the corn to the coolies he sometimes employed in cutting his crops, drawing water, and so on.

My mother had a brother, by name Hanuman, who was in the service of the Company Bahadur, and was a Jemadar in an infantry battalion. He had come home on leave for six months, and on his way to his own home, he stayed with my father. My uncle was a very handsome man, and of great personal strength. He used of an evening to sit on the seat before our house, and relate the wonders of the world he had seen, and the prosperity of the great Company Bahadur he served, to a crowd of eager listeners, who with open mouths and staring eyes took in all his marvels as undoubted truths. None of his hearers were more attentive than myself, and from these recitals I imbibed a strong desire to enter the world, and try the fortune of a soldier.

Nothing else could I think of, day or night. The rank of Jemadar I looked on as quite equal to that of Ghazidin Hydar, the King of Oudh himself; in fact, never having seen the latter, I naturally considered my uncle as of even more importance. He had such a splendid necklace of gold beads, and a curious bright red coat, covered with gold buttons; and, above all, he appeared to have an unlimited supply of gold mohurs.[2] I longed for the time when I might possess the same, which I then thought would be directly I became the Company Bahadur's servant.

My uncle had observed how attentive I was to all his stories, and how military ardour had inflamed my breast, and certainly he did all in his power to encourage me. He never said anything about it before my father and mother, or the priest; still, he repeatedly told me privately that if I wished to be a soldier, he would take me back with him on his return to the regiment. How I longed to mention this to my mother, but dared not for I well knew her dearest wish was for me to become a priest. However, one day when I had been reading with Duleep Ram about the mighty battles fought by the gods, I fairly told him my wish to become a soldier. How horrified he seemed! How he reproached me, declaring that all the instruction he had so laboured to impart to me was thrown away, and that half the stories my uncle had told me were false; that I might be flogged, and certainly should be defiled by entering the Company's service. A hundred other terrors he conjured up, but these had no effect on me.

The priest immediately went to my parents and informed them of my determination, and thus broke to them the subject I had not the courage to tell. To my great surprise my father made no objections; these all came from my mother, who wept, scolded, entreated, and threatened me, ending by imploring me to give up the idea, and abused my father for not preventing such a catastrophe. At this particular period of which I now write a lawsuit was impending over my father, about his right to a mango grove of some 400 trees, and he thought that having a son in the Company Bahadur's service would be the means of getting his case attended to in the law courts of Lucknow; for it was well known that a petition sent by a soldier, through his commanding officer, who forwarded it on to the Resident sahib[3] in Lucknow, generally had prompt attention paid to it, and carried more weight than even the bribes and party interest of a mere subject of the King of Oudh.

Shortly after my parents had been informed of my desire to take service with Company Bahadur my uncle left them to proceed to his own home fifty miles away. Although my mother never expressed any wish for him to pay another visit when he was about to return to his regiment on the expiration of his leave, he told her that he intended to do so, and that he should take me with him if I were still of the same mind. I walked the first few miles with him on his journey, and made him tell me all about the service I wished to enter, over and over again.

Upon my return home I had to sustain the united attacks of the priest and my mother. They tried every inducement to make me give up the idea. My mother even cursed the day her brother had set foot in our house, but all they could get from me was a promise that I would think over the matter. This I did, and every day became more and more determined to follow my uncle. I now felt idle, and did very little else than learn to wrestle or play with sword-sticks, and consequently neglected my father's fields, which caused me to fall under his displeasure. However a threat from him that I should never be allowed to see my uncle again had the effect of bringing me a little to my senses, and my father had no occasion to find fault with me afterwards.

The months passed away, and the rainy season had ended. I was engaged in cutting sugar-cane, with my back towards the road, when I was called by name by someone on a pony. I soon recognized my uncle and flew to his embrace. After inquiries for my father and mother, he asked me if I wished to be a soldier still, and looked pleased when I answered so decidedly, ‘Yes’. He told me I was a fine young fellow and that I should go with him.

My uncle remained a few days at our house, during which time, having my father to back him up, he in a measure succeeded in bringing my mother to think it was my destiny to be a soldier, and her fate to part with her son. The priest was requested to look at my horoscope and discover the lucky day for my departure, which he informed us, in the evening, would be at six o’clock in the morning of the fourth day from that day, if no thunder was heard during the period. How anxiously I watched the clouds during those days! How I prayed to the gods of the rain and clouds! And in the evening of the third day, when some dark clouds came up, I was in despair lest rain should fall, and fate be against me.

Duleep, the priest, who really loved me, gave me lots of advice, and made me promise never to disgrace my brahminical thread.[4] He also gave me a charm in which was some dust a thousand Brahmins had trod at holy Allahabad, and he assured me that this charm was so powerful that as long as I kept it no harm could ever befall me. He bestowed on me likewise a book of our holy poems. My father bought me a pony, but gave me no money, as he considered I was now under my uncle’s care, and that he could well support me.

The morning came unclouded. It was 10 October 1812,[5] and at six o’clock in the morning I and my uncle left my home to enter what for me was an unknown world. Just before starting, my mother violently kissed me, and gave me six gold mohurs sewn in a cloth bag, but being convinced that it was her fate to part with me, she uttered no words but moaned piteously. My worldly baggage when I left home consisted of my pony, my bag of gold mohurs, a small brass bowl and string,[6] three brass dishes, one iron dish and spoon, two changes of clothes, a smart turban, a small axe (for self-protection), and a pair of shoes. My uncle's baggage greatly exceeded mine; it was rolled up in a large bundle and carried by a coolie from village to village. This poor man considered himself amply rewarded for his day's work by our giving him whatever bread was left over after the daily meal.

1. There were three grades of native officer. The junior was Jemadar; the next was Subedar, or Rissaldar in the Cavalry. The senior was Subedar- or Rissaldar-Major, of which there was only one in each infantry battalion or cavalry regiment.

2. Gold mohurs were part of the coinage of the Mughal Empire.

3. The East India Company was represented at the court of the King of Oudh by a Resident, who was a senior civil or military officer of the Company's service. His duties were supposedly advisory, but in fact the King knew that behind the advice lay the ultimate sanction of force.

4. This thread is worn next to the skin, hanging loosely across the body from the shoulder, and is never removed, not even for bathing. It is one of the distinguishing marks of an orthodox Brahmin.

5. Sita Ram is inclined to be hazy over dates, which is not surprising in view of his age when he was writing his memoirs, and the fact that the Christian calendar differs from the Hindu. He probably means 1814, not 1812, since he says he was seventeen years old when he set off to join the army.

6. None but a Brahmin can cook for a Brahmin, or draw water for a Brahmin. Hence the small brass bowl with a string to let down into a well to draw water.

Joining the Regiment

Sita Ram describes his journey to Agra, or Akbarabad as it was then called, where his uncle's regiment formed part of the garrison. He also tells of his enlistment into the Army.

Travel in India during the break-up of the Mughal empire was a hazardous business. Bands of armed robbers roamed the countryside and highway robbery was commonplace—‘In those days only the strong man armed could guard his goods, and then only until a stronger than he should come.'[1] But perhaps the greatest hazard came from the thugs, or stranglers, who murdered partly for religious motives, and partly for gain. The thugs travelled in bands, posing as innocent travellers, and joined up with other travellers until the moment had come to strike. They believed themselves to be servants of the goddess Kali, wife of Siva, who had taught them their craft in return for her protection, and the yellow scarf, knotted at one end, with which they strangled their victims, represented the hem of Kali's robe. Murder by strangulation was therefore a divine mission, while the booty obtained thereby was the thugs' earthly reward.

Their secrets were so closely kept that it was many years before the British stumbled on the truth about thuggee, and it took a great deal longer before the evil was eradicated. Some of the bands operated under the patronage of powerful landowners, and there was in any case a conspiracy of silence which was hard to penetrate. A special department was set up to stamp out Thuggee, and for much of its existence it was headed by Sir William Sleeman, an officer of the Bengal Army, whose determination and patience largely contributed to the defeat of Thuggee. Over 3,000 Thugs were convicted between 1831 and 1837, and some of them boasted of 700 or more murders. Sita Ram's party had a narrow escape from a band of thugs who fell in with them on their way to Agra. He gives a good description of how the thugs operated, and of how one of his companions was strangled.

The story of his first encounter, as a credulous Indian village boy, with the almost mythical British, rings true to life. It is also descriptive of the almost paternal relationships between officers and sepoys which then existed in the Bengal Army. Later in his memoirs Sita Ram laments the weakening of this relationship, but it is only fair to say that British officers of the Madras and Bombay Armies were critical of their colleagues in the Bengal Army, believing that they paid far too much attention to the religious scruples and susceptibilities of their high-caste sepoys, which in turn led to a weakening of discipline.

My uncle and I went one march in the morning. We rested during the heat of the day under a tree, and in the evening we marched the same distance as we had in the morning. For the night we always put up at a serai[2] whenever this was possible. On the third day we arrived at a village called Dersungpor where two sepoys of my uncle's regiment, whose leave had finished, joined us. One was called Tillukdaree Gheer, and the other Deonarain. They appeared delighted to meet my uncle and treated him with great respect. Deonarain was accompanied by his younger brother, who was hoping to enlist. They were all carrying swords, and Tillukdaree also had a blunderbuss, called a 'young tiger'. We looked a rather formidable party, and felt secure against the bandits and thugs who then infested the roads.

After about three or four days a party of itinerant musicians came up with us and begged that we should join forces for the sake of protection. They consisted of two men with drums, four men with sitars,[3] two men with cymbals, and one with a kind of trumpet. They told us that they were on their way to attend a marriage festival at a town which lay on our way.

For several days everything went smoothly, and the musicians enlivened our march by playing pretty airs. But during the night of the fourth day my uncle, happening to be awake, discovered that all the musicians had collected together and were in some earnest debate, speaking in a low tone of voice and in a tongue[4] which he could not understand. Alarmed at what he saw, he immediately aroused the other sepoys and told them he believed that the musicians were in reality thugs. He then appointed one of our party to watch them while the rest of us again laid down to sleep.

The next morning my uncle told the musicians that he was obliged to make long marches, and that therefore they would be unable to keep up with us. They, however, begged to be allowed to accompany us, and at the same time expressed great fear of being robbed on the road. Nevertheless my uncle marched very early the next morning, leaving them behind. We went some eight miles on the high road, and then branched off by a side path, intending to join the road again some thirty miles farther on.

The next four days passed without incident. At the evening's halting-place on the fourth day we were joined by a party of about twelve men, carrying bundles of bamboos which are used for making pipe-stems. These men begged to be allowed to join us for protection, as the musicians had done. In the morning, when it was light, I fancied that one of these men was remarkably like one of the former party, and mentioned this to my uncle who went to them and entered into conversation. But their language was different from that of the musicians, their clothes were very dirty, and they looked like coolies. Still he was on his guard, and appointed one of the sepoys to keep awake and watch the movements of these people.

During the night, after we had halted, I could not go to sleep for a long time, as I believed these men were also thugs. However, in spite of my endeavours to keep awake, I fell asleep eventually, but was shortly afterwards awakened by a noise like a cock crowing close by.[5] I sat up, and in a moment one or two of these men were by the side of the sleepers. I shouted loudly, and my uncle jumped up with his sword drawn, and rushed at them. Although this was the work of a moment, the fiends had managed to strangle the brother of Deonarain with a silk cord, and had rendered Tillukdaree senseless. He was just saved by my uncle who cut down the thug standing over him. The others disappeared immediately, leaving their bundles of sticks behind them. However, in this short space, the thugs had managed to steal my uncle's gold beads, worth 250 rupees,[6] and Tillukdaree's blunderbuss. He had fallen asleep when he was supposed to be on watch.

After all this had happened, we went to the village nearby and roused the entire population, but no-one showed the slightest inclination to pursue the blood-thirsty murders. We passed the remainder of the night on the outskirts of the village, having carried with us the dead body of Deonarain's brother. In the morning we found the bamboos still at our former camping place, and my uncle sold them to a tobacco merchant for 46 rupees, but not without an altercation with the village headman who claimed that they belonged to him, by right of their having been left on his ground. We stayed a complete day at the village in order to perform the funeral rites for Deonarain's unfortunate brother. Fortunately for Deonarain's comfort we were only a few miles from the holy Ganges, and he had the satisfaction of seeing the priest cast his brother's ashes into the stream, thus securing his brother rest in our Hindu heaven. Tillukdaree was so weak from the effect of the thug's cord round his throat that he was obliged to hire a pony cart, and we proceeded, now a mournful party, on our way.

My uncle now allowed no parties of any kind to join us, although several begged hard to do so since they saw we were armed. Nothing of any consequence took place during the rest of the journey so far as I can remember, until we arrived at Agra, where my uncle's regiment was then stationed.[7] We arrived there on 14 November, and when we came near the lines we met several sepoys of the regiment going down to the Jumna to bathe. They all embraced my uncle, and, before we came to the lines, some thirty men of his Company came running out to meet him and asked a thousand questions. My uncle went to his own house, which had been kept neat and clean by a havildar who had lived in it during my uncle's absence.

After bathing, and eating the morning meal, my uncle put on full regimentals and went to pay his respects to the Adjutant sahib,[8] and Commanding Officer. He took me with him. I was rather dreading this because I had never yet seen a sahib and imagined they were terrible to look on and of great stature—at least seven feet tall! In those days there were only a few sahibs in Oudh; only one or two sahib Residents in Lucknow, where I had never been.[9] In the villages of my country the most extraordinary ideas existed about them, and any one who had chanced to see a sahib told the most curious stories. In fact nothing was too far-fetched to be believed. It was said that they were born from an egg which grew on a tree, and this idea still exists in remote villages. Had a memsahib[10] come suddenly into some of our villages, she would, if young and handsome, have been considered to be some kind of fairy, and would probably have been worshipped; but should she have been old and ugly, the whole village would have run away to hide in the jungle, believing her to be a witch. It is therefore hardly surprising that I should have been so terrified at the prospect of seeing a sahib for the first time in my life.

I remember once, when I was attending a fair at the Taj Mahal in Agra, an old woman said she had always believed that sahibs came from eggs which grew on a tree; but that morning she had seen a sahib with a fairy by his side. The fairy was covered with feathers of the most beautiful colours, her face was as white as milk, and the sahib had to keep his hand on her shoulders to prevent her from flying away. All this the old woman had seen with her own eyes, and she swore it was true. I am not so ignorant now, of course, but I would have believed it when first I arrived at Agra. I afterwards often saw that sahib driving out with his lady. She wore a tippet made from peacock feathers, and the old woman had mistaken this for wings.

We went to the Adjutant's house, which was four times the size of the headman's house in my village. He was on the verandah, with a long stick, measuring young men who were recruits. He was very young, not as tall as myself, and had no whiskers nor moustache. His face was quite smooth and looked more like a woman's than a man's. This was the first sahib I had ever seen, and he did not fill me with much awe. I did not believe he could be much of a warrior with a face as smooth as that since among us it is considered a disgrace to be clean-shaven; in fact a smooth-faced soldier is usually the butt for many jokes. However he banged those young recruits' heads against the wall in a manner which showed he had no fear, and they looked as if they thought he was about to kill them.

After he had finished with the measuring, the Adjutant took notice of my uncle, and to my surprise spoke to him in my own language. He seemed glad to see him, asked after his welfare, and touched his sword.[11] He then asked who I was, and on being informed that I had come to enlist and was my uncle's nephew, he told my uncle to take me to the Doctor sahib, to whom he wrote a letter. I was astonished at the speed of his writing; in less time than I could have put water to the ink and written one line, he had filled a page, which he then doubled up and gave to my uncle, and we went to the Doctor sahib's house.

This was even bigger than the Adjutant's. My uncle told me that the Doctor was married and had several children. He was at home and we were ordered into his presence. A chair was provided for my uncle, but no notice was taken of me so I squatted on the ground. My uncle made me stand up, and told me afterwards that it was bad manners to sit down in the presence of a sahib. After reading the note, the Doctor ordered me to strip, but I was so ashamed I could not move, for there was a memsahib in the room. She was sitting at a table covered with a sheet, and feeding two children with eggs—those unclean things![12] I began to regret having followed my uncle, and remembered the priest's warning about being defiled. However I was ordered sharply to take off my clothes, and both the children began calling out—'Papa says you are to take your clothes off! Don't you understand? Donkey, pig, owl!'—and the Doctor joined in, saying I was a fool and an ignorant villager. Then the children cried out—'Oh, mamma, is he covered with hair?' I was so ashamed that I ran out onto the verandah, but my uncle came out and told me not to be afraid. No harm would be done to me. The Doctor then pushed me into an empty room and examined me, by thrusting his hand against my stomach, which nearly made me vomit. Then he opened my eyelids with such violence that tears came into my eyes, and he thumped my chest. After this he pronounced me fit and ceased tormenting me—to my great relief.

My uncle next went to pay his respects to the Colonel sahib. We were kept outside for an hour, and then ordered to approach. I was now in such a state of terror, not knowing what horror might next befall me, that my legs knocked together. I imagined that the Colonel sahib must be terrible to gaze upon—he commanded one thousand men—his wish was law! Judge my surprise when I saw an old man, very short and stout, without a hair on his head or face, and with a skin of a bright red colour. He was smoking a magnificent hookah.[13] He got up to welcome my uncle, and after I was introduced spoke very kindly to me, telling me to be a good boy and imitate my uncle in everything. I have said this was the first time in my life I had ever seen any sahibs. I had now seen three, and how different they were to my ideas of them. I could not believe they were so brave as they were reputed to be; they were all smaller than my uncle and did not look half as strong. And what a number of curious things they had in their houses. I could not imagine what they did with them. In one corner of the Colonel's room was a table full of glass cups of all sorts and sizes, and in another corner a stand with seven or eight guns. The walls were hung with the heads of animals —tigers, stags, antelope, and other deer. The sahib was wearing a tight blue coat, buttoned up to the throat with big brass buttons, and with two lumps of what I then thought was gold on his shoulders.[14] He wore white pantaloons, and long black boots with golden tassels on either side. Although I was not struck with his size or strength, still there was something in his eyes which I shall never forget; they were like the eyes of a hawk and seemed to look through and through one. After we had left, my uncle told me that the Colonel was a renowned sportsman who had killed as many as nine tigers.

In a few days I was sent to begin my drill. It is a day I shall always remember, for is it not impressed for ever on my mind? The parade-ground was covered by parties of six or eight men, performing the most extraordinary movements I had ever seen, and these to orders in a language of which I did not understand a single word.[15] I felt inclined to laugh, and stood astonished at the sight. However a violent wrench of my ear by the drill havildar [sergeant] soon brought me to my senses. I had to attend drill for many months, and one day I happened to forget how to do something and was so severely cuffed on the head by the drill havildar that I fell down senseless. I complained to my uncle who was very angry with the drill havildar. Although he never dared to strike me again, from that day on he bullied me in every other way and used to abuse me at every opportunity. As I had gone to great pains to learn my duties, I resented this treatment very much and had almost made up my mind to run away. The drill havildar told the Adjutant that I was obstinate and stupid, and would never make a soldier.

I told my uncle of the treatment I was receiving, and said I repented of ever having come with him. But he encouraged me, and one day the Colonel sahib came to inspect the recruits and I managed to do my drill to his satisfaction. He ordered the Adjutant to test me in the whole of my drill, and the Adjutant told the Colonel that I was fit to join the ranks. I so longed to wear a red coat, and to have a musket of my own. Besides which, I had only been eight months at my drill, and out of a party of seventy-eight recruits, many of whom had enlisted before me, I was the only one selected to join the ranks. Few were ever sent to do this, unless in war-time, until they had been at drill for a year, and often for even longer periods.

1. Twilight of the Mughuls by Percival Spear, Cambridge University Press, 1951.

2. A resting place for travellers where stabling was usually provided for animals.

3. A sitar is a kind of violin which has recently become popularized by The Beatles.

4. India is, of course, a land of many languages, and of even more dialects.

5. The tactics adopted by the thugs (more properly thags, meaning deceivers) seldom varied. They began by winning the confidence of those to whom they had attached themselves, and would if necessary travel many miles and for several days until any suspicion of their real intentions had been dispelled. Then, when the leader of the band judged that the moment had come to strike, they would prepare their victims' graves, and each select a victim to strangle. The signal to strike was usually the cry 'Bring the tobacco!', but this was sometimes varied by the sound of a cock crowing. The actual strangling was the work of a moment, the handkerchief, or silken cord, having a knot at one end to assist the stranglers' grip. Once the deed was done, the bodies were searched and then buried, the booty shared, and the thugs moved on in search of other victims. At the end of the expedition, which might last several months, the band dispersed to their own homes, and returned to their peaceful avocations, until they were summoned by their leader to assemble for another foray. Few thugs showed any remorse for the murders they had committed, believing they were serving a religious end, and many of them were respected members of society. The ramifications of Thuggee ran deep and many a landowner, or minor rajah, was in receipt of 'hush-money' from the gangs.

6. The rupee at this time was worth about two shillings.

7. Agra, which stands on the banks of the River Jumna, about three hours' drive from Delhi, was the capital of India during the reign of the great Akbar, and is of course famed for the exquisite Taj Mahal, built by Akbar's son, the Emperor Shah Jehan. It had become an important British military garrison by the time Sita Ram arrived there in 1814.

8. The addition of the word sahib to a title, rank, or name, signifies respect, but during British rule in India it came to represent the British, or gora log, i.e. the white people, or Europeans.

9. The East India Company's Resident at the court of the King of Oudh had a numerous staff, as well as a substantial escort of troops, commanded by British officers. It would be to these sahibs that Sita Ram is referring, although he had never seen them himself.

10. Memsahib, the female equivalent of sahib, was usually taken to mean the wife of a European. I am not aware that it was much used by Indians to signify an Indian lady of rank.

11. Sita Ram's uncle, as a mark of respect, would have handed the Adjutant the hilt of his sword to touch. This custom was followed in the Indian Cavalry until 1940, or later.

12. Sita Ram, as a Brahmin, would have been a strict vegetarian, for whom even eggs would be tabu.

13. The smoking of hookahs, or hubble-bubbles, or water-pipes, was part of British social life in India until about the middle of the nineteenth century when for some reason it died out. There were even some women who smoked hookahs, and the spacious Anglo-Indian household of those days usually included a servant whose sole task was looking after the sahib's hookahs and providing the tobacco. These servants were known as hookahbadars.

14. Sita Ram is here referring to the gold-lace epaulettes of a field officer.

15. It is only within the last three years that the Indian Army has adopted Hindi words of command in place of English.

The Wind of
Madness

In this chapter Sita Ram describes his experiences during the Mutiny of the Bengal Native Army which first broke out at Berhampore in Bengal in March 1857, and continued until Oudh was finally cleared of the rebels two years later. Sita Ram gives us an excellent example of the conflict of loyalties that result from an uprising of this kind and, although he chose to remain loyal to the Government he had served so long, he is honest in admitting that he feared he might well be serving a losing cause. His account of his doubts and fears reminds me of a similar situation some years ago when an Arab officer of the South Arabian Army took me into his confidence and told me of his dilemma at the time when nationalism was gathering force in Aden. He too chose to remain loyal to his salt and was, like Sita Ram, called a traitor by his compatriots.

The Indian Mutiny was basically a revolt by a conservative and traditionalist society against what seemed to be a threat to their religion and ancient customs. There were many causes for the Mutiny, but au fond it was the imagined threat to their religion that caused so many Hindu and Mahommedan sepoys to break out into revolt. However, all this did not happen in a night, as we are sometimes led to believe in novels of the Mutiny, but was a slow simmering over many years that only came to the boil in the spring of 1857. And even then many of the mutineers hurried home from their garrisons and took no further part in the proceedings, leaving it to their more politically-motivated or fanatical comrades to pursue the rebellion against the British. It is this which makes the Mutiny less a nationalist uprising than a military rebellion pure and simple but it is of course true that there were many in India, or at least in Hindustan, who sought to utilize the soldiers' mutiny to drive the British back into the sea whence they had come.

Field-Marshal Lord Roberts, one of the Indian Army's best-loved Commanders-in-Chief, fought throughout the Mutiny as an officer in the Bengal Horse Artillery. In his view the causes of the Mutiny were as follows. First, the fears of the high-caste Hindu soldiers that their religion was in danger, and this fear was in turn communicated to their Mahommedan comrades. Second, the annexation of Oudh by Lord Dalhousie, which offended local sentiment, and resulted in the loss by the sepoys of their former privileged standing in the courts: they could scarcely claim special privileges in what was now British territory. Third, the affair of the cartridges which were supposed to be smeared with a mixture of cow's fat and lard for preservative purposes, and which the sepoy had to bite before loading his weapon. Fourth, pampering of the sepoy in the Bengal Army, which gave him an undue sense of his own importance. Fifth, the dangerous disproportion in numbers between the European and Indian troops. It is astonishing to learn that in 1857, when the Mutiny broke out, there were only 21,197 British troops in India, whereas the Bengal, Madras, and Bombay Native Armies totalled 277,000 men; and this figure does not include the para-military forces such as the armed police. Sixth, dissatisfaction among the sepoys over various administrative measures, such as the withdrawal of field allowance for troops serving in the Punjab and Sind, and the insistence, after November 1856, that sepoys must undertake on enlistment to serve beyond the sea. Most high-caste Hindus believed that service beyond the Kala Pani, or Black Water, would inevitably destroy their caste and the new regulation was regarded as yet another nail in the coffin of their religion.

Finally, and possibly most importantly, Lord Roberts places much of the blame for the Mutiny on the shoulders of the British officers of the Bengal Native Army who were too complacent, too old, and too susceptible to the prejudices of their men to take a firm line with them. Although the Bombay Army recruited high caste sepoys from the same areas as the Bengal Army, these men were allowed no special privileges vis à vis the low caste and outcaste races who supplied a most trustworthy ingredient to the Bombay Army. At the siege of Multan the Bengal sepoys refused to dig in the earthworks because of their caste but their co-religionists in the Bombay Army worked without demur. In the Bombay Army promotion was by selection, whereas in Bengal it was by seniority, which accounts for Sita Ram having to wait until he was nearly sixty before becoming a jemadar. But the most damning indictment of the Bengal Army is contained in a footnote in Lord Robert's Forty-One Years in India, in which he wrote:

'It is curious to note how nearly every military officer who held a command or a high position on the staff in Bengal when the Mutiny broke out, disappeared from the scene within the first few weeks, and was never heard of officially again. . . . Two Generals of divisions were removed from their commands, seven Brigadiers were found wanting in the hour of need, and out of the seventy-three regiments of Regular Cavalry and Infantry which mutinied, only four Commanding Officers were given other commands, younger officers being selected to raise and command the new regiments.'

Despite the strains to which he was subjected, Sita Ram remained loyal, and so no doubt did many others of his kind about whom we are never told. The mutineers considered him to be a traitor and carried him off to Lucknow to be put to death by torture but he was rescued by a roving party of European Moss-Troopers and eventually joined one of the new regiments raised in the Punjab to replace the Bengal regiments. This must have been the time he met his future Commanding Officer, Norgate, who was serving in the 12th Punjab Infantry, and who may have been the officer who relieved him of the responsibility of commanding the firing party that executed his son as a rebel.

After the fall of Multan and the total defeat of the Sikhs at Gujerat, the English took possession of all the land of the Punjab, or Five Rivers. The mighty power of the Sikh nation became as dust and the mantle of rule descended upon the Sirkar, the great Company Bahadur. The sirdars were all taken prisoner and their troops, deprived of their weapons, were disbanded and sent to their homes. English regiments were stationed all over the Punjab—at Lahore, Wazirabad, Jhelum, Rawal Pindi, Attock, Peshawar, and many other places—without any further opposition. Truly, the English are a remarkable people; within six months barracks rose out of the ground as if by magic. The sahibs built houses, police were organized, and the country appeared as if it had belonged to the Sirkar for many years.

My regiment was now sent to Jullundur. Two regiments of old Sikh soldiers were enlisted for the Sirkar[1] and young Sikhs were taken into the native regiments. This annoyed the sepoys exceedingly, for the Sikhs were disliked by the Hindustanis who considered them to be unclean and were not permitted to associate with them. Their position was very uncomfortable for a long time but after a while this dislike to some extent disappeared. However, these men always kept to themselves and were regarded as interlopers by the older sepoys. They were never as smart as we were on parade and their practice of using curds to clean their long hair gave them an extremely disagreeable odour, but many of them became like Hindus after they had been away from their own country for a long time.

No wars took place for several years in Hindustan and nothing particular occurred apart from several innovations which were introduced into the Army, and into the Civil Courts, which caused great offence among the people.[2] In 1855 a small war broke out in Bengal with some jungle people called Santhals,[3] and my regiment formed part of the force and was stationed near Raniganj, not far from Calcutta. It was there that I first saw the iron road and the steam monster and this was more wonderful than anything I had ever seen before. When I asked the people about it they said they believed that the English put some powerful demon into each iron box, and it was his efforts to escape which made the wheels turn round. However I saw the water put in, and the coals lighted under it, but I am so ignorant of how it works that if an officer had not told me that it was all the force of steam, I might easily have believed that this demon fed on wood, coal, or stones, and drank gallons of water.

I went down to Calcutta in the train but it went so fast that it nearly took away my senses. As it neared Calcutta all kinds of low caste people entered the train and behaved as if they were equal to everyone. This is not good and caused great annoyance to many. I was amazed by what I saw in Calcutta but what is the use of describing it to you, my Lord, who know it so well? The ships—what can I possibly say? They were a hundred times larger than I had expected. No wonder the sahibs can travel all over the world. Each ship could carry a regiment. The Lord sahib's house[4] was very big, and if every nobleman in England lives in a house as big as that, what a wonderful country England must be! I noticed in this magnificent city that the sahibs seldom spoke to each other and I was told they did not know one another. But can this be possible if they all come from such a small island?

The Santhals used bows, arrows, and large sharp axes, but they always dispersed when we fired on them. At first it was reported that they used poisoned arrows, and for this reason they were much feared, but we soon discovered that this was not the case. After a good deal of marching through thick jungle, and after guarding the main road by the Sone river throughout one hot weather, the rebellion was put down and my regiment was sent to ————. I was told by some of the Santhals that they rebelled because they could obtain no justice from the Civil Courts. They had no money with which to bribe the native officials and their complaints were all against the rich landlords and moneylenders, who had managed to get these simple folk into their clutches. I cannot vouch for the truth of this but it was certainly a curious war. In one part of the jungle we were firing at them, while in another the Sirkar was providing them with cart-loads of rice.

There was now a rumour that the Sirkar was going to take Oudh from the Nawab. This led to great excitement within the army, which was largely composed of men from Oudh. Many of them did not much care whether the Sirkar took Oudh or not but these were men who owned no property there. Nevertheless an undefined dislike and disquiet took possession of all of us. During the year [1856] the Sirkar removed the Nawab to Calcutta and took over the government of the Kingdom of Oudh. Regiments of local infantry and cavalry were formed, officered by English officers, and a number of Assistant Commissioner sahibs were brought in. Many of these officers came from the Bombay and Madras Armies and were totally ignorant of the language, manners, and customs of the people, and the same was true of all the sahibs who came from Bengal from the college.[5] The occupation of the country was effected without any open resistance at the time. It took place so quickly that the people did not have time to combine against it but the minds of all the Taluqdars[6] and headmen were excited against the Sirkar, which in their view had acted dishonourably, and had been unfair to the Nawab.[7] There were plenty of interested people to keep this feeling alive. They assured everyone that the estates of the rich would soon be confiscated by the Sirkar, which could easily manipulate the law courts to show that the present owners had no right to these estates. The truth was that so many people in Oudh had acquired property by methods which the Government would never recognize that they began to fear an inquiry. Since all these people had large numbers of relations, retainers, and servants living with them, who were all interested parties, it explains the great excitement prevailing in Oudh at the time, and consequently throughout the Sirkar's army.

It is my humble opinion that this seizing of Oudh filled the minds of the sepoys with distrust and led them to plot against the Government. Agents of the Nawab of Oudh and also of the King of Delhi were sent all over India to discover the temper of the army. They worked upon the feelings of the sepoys, telling them how treacherously the foreigners had behaved towards their king. They invented ten thousand lies and promises to persuade the soldiers to mutiny and turn against their masters, the English, with the object of restoring the Emperor of Delhi to the throne.

They maintained that this was wholly within the army's powers if the soldiers would only act together and do as they were advised.

It chanced that about this time the Sirkar sent parties of men from each regiment to different garrisons for instruction in the use of the new rifle.[8] These men performed the new drill for some time until a report got about, by some means or other, that the cartridges used for these new rifles were greased with the fat of cows and pigs. The men from our regiment wrote to others in the regiment telling them of this, and there was soon excitement in every regiment. Some men pointed out that in forty years' service nothing had ever been done by the Sirkar to insult their religion, but as I have already mentioned the sepoys' minds had been inflamed by the seizure of Oudh. Interested parties were quick to point out that the great aim of the English was to turn us all into Christians, and they had therefore introduced the cartridge in order to bring this about, since both Mahommedans and Hindus would be defiled by using it.[9]

I reported this curious story to my officer but no notice was taken. He only told me not to talk about it. Some time later an order was read out to the regiment from the Commander-in-Chief, or Governor-General sahib, saying that the Sirkar had not used any objectionable fat but that in future the men could make up their own cartridges and use their own grease. They could then be satisfied that the Sirkar had no intention whatsoever of hurting their feelings or breaking their caste. However the very reading out of this order was seized upon by many as proof that the Sirkar had broken our caste, since otherwise the order would never have been issued. What was the use of a denial if it had not been the Government's intention originally to break our caste?

It was the time of year for furlough[10]—that is the month of April—and it was my turn to go on leave. Before I went I told my Commanding Officer what I had heard, and I warned him that great madness had possessed the minds of all men. I could not say what shape the discontent would take, but I never thought the entire army would mutiny—only those men who might have suffered as a result of annexation of Oudh—and at present only a few of the really bad characters were disaffected. The Colonel sahib was of the opinion that the excitement, which even he

could not fail to see,[11] would pass off, as it had often done before, and he recommended me to go to my home.

I arrived at my own village without hearing anything out of the ordinary on the road, but shortly afterwards we heard that the troops of Meerut and Delhi had risen and killed their officers, and had proclaimed the King of Delhi as Emperor. They were excited to revolt because a complete regiment[12] had been cast into jail, having been loaded with irons which destroyed their honour. This was such an extraordinary story that I refused to believe it, considering it a story invented to inflame the minds of the populace, but the rumour gathered strength daily, so I went to the Deputy Commissioner to enquire whether it was true. I could not do this openly without arousing suspicion, for at this time all the office staff were on the watch for all who came to the office. I went to the Deputy Commissioner's house with a petition, but the chaprassi[13] refused to take it in to the sahib, saying the orders stated that no-one would be received except during office hours. However I managed to see the sahib, and I told him the tale I had heard and asked if there was any truth in it. The sahib said neither one thing nor the other but asked me a number of questions to discover how much I knew and what effect it was having on the minds of the people in my district. Finally the sahib admitted that he had heard the rumour—as I had known from the beginning by the questions he asked me—but said that the reports were very vague.

Had I asked some important Indian official, he would probably have denied any knowledge of the facts, and the more vehemently he denied any knowledge, the more I would have been certain that he knew all about it. Had I persisted, he would have attempted to discover my own feelings on the subject, and then, if I had committed myself by wishing the mutineers well, he would have informed against me, even though he himself might have been heart and soul in their favour.

By the time I returned to my village the whole place was talking about the news. In a short time the entire country was in a ferment[14] and every regiment was reported to be ripe for mutiny. Reports came in every day that the regiments at the different stations had risen and killed their officers. I went again to see the Deputy Commissioner and offered to collect the furlough men of my own regiment, as well as any pensioners who could use arms. He thanked me and promised to let me know if I would be required to do this. Shortly afterwards the regiments at Lucknow, Sitapore, and other stations in Oudh broke out into open mutiny, and the country was overrun with sepoys from these regiments. Many of these men returned to their homes and had nothing further to do with the mutiny, other than having been in a regiment which had mutinied.

`

I now discovered that I was being watched. I was suspected of giving information to the civilian officials. One day a large party of sepoys from one of the mutinied regiments came through my village, and I tried to persuade them to go quietly to their houses. I explained to them the folly of going against the English Government, but these men were so intoxicated with the plunder they had taken, and by their hope of reward from the Emperor of Delhi, that they turned on me and were about to shoot me on the spot for having dared to speak out in favour of the English Government. They called me a traitor, and ended by taking me prisoner. They put heavy irons on me and a chain round my neck, declaring they would take me to Lucknow where they would receive a large reward for having captured me, and where my punishment would be to have molten lead poured down my throat for having dared uphold the English rule under which I had served and eaten salt for so many years. I was treated with every possible indignity. My captors boasted of the deeds they had done—how the sahibs had been so easily killed, or terrified into running away into the jungles like hares—and they were convinced that the English rule had ended throughout India. I never saw men behave in such a shameless fashion—not even during Holi.[15] They all believed they would be made princes for what they had done, and debated among themselves about the offices they would be given by the King of Delhi. I could not discover what they had done, other than that they had shot down their officers on the parade ground, looted the station without any resistance, and set it on fire. While we were on the march some people informed them that there was a European regiment not far behind, and their boasting was redoubled. They would immediately annihilate it! This was what they said in public but inwardly they were terrified of coming up against the English. The European regiment never materialized, nor indeed was there the slightest truth in the report. I was relieved to hear this since they had told me that I should be shot at once if any Europeans appeared on the scene.

The leader of this party was a sepoy, although there were two subedars with it. He came one day and showed me a proclamation from the King of Delhi. It called upon all the sepoys to rise and destroy the English, promising great rewards and promotion if the men of any regiment would mutiny and kill their officers. It stated that the English Sirkar intended to make all Brahmins into Christians, which had in fact been proved correct, and in proof of it one hundred Padres were about to be stationed in Oudh.[16] Caste was going to be broken by forcing everyone to eat beef and pork. The sepoys were exhorted not to allow this to happen, but to fight for their religion and drive the detested foreigners out of the country. It also stated that the king had received information from the Sultan of Turkey that all the English soldiers had been destroyed by the Russians;[17] there were only left the few regiments remaining in India; and these were all separated by great distances and could easily be surrounded and destroyed. This proclamation was printed on yellow paper and was said to have been issued by order of the king. Every man who heard it believed every word of it. Even I was impressed by it. I had never known the Sirkar to interfere with our religion or our caste in all the years since I had been a soldier, but I was nevertheless filled with doubt. I remembered the treatment of many regiments with regard to field allowance—how it had first been promised and then withheld. I could not forget that the Sirkar had seized Oudh without due cause.

I had also remarked the increase of Padre sahibs during recent years, who stood up in the streets of our cities and told the people that their cherished religion was all false, and who exhorted them to become Christians. They always maintained that they were not employed by the Sirkar, but how could they have acted like this without the Government's sanction? Everyone believed that they were secretly employed by the Government; why else should they take such trouble? Then I remembered how the Sirkar had been my protector, and that I had eaten its salt for over forty years, and I was determined never to betray it so long as it continued to rule but to do all that I could to support it. But, my Lord, you must not forget that I was bound with chains at this time, and to all appearance being taken to a terrible death. As each day passed and I heard that city after city, garrison after garrison, had fallen into the hands of the local population, I must confess that the thought passed through my mind that the mighty Company's rule was passing away. All its guns had been captured, and also all its arsenals—how could I help thinking otherwise? However I still had faith in the incredible good fortune of the Sirkar, which had always been so wonderful and marvellous. I also believe that those who had broken their word and committed such crimes could not expect to have good fortune for long.

When the party of sepoys with whom I was drew near to Lucknow, from some orders they pretended to have received direct from the Nana of Bithur[18] the route was changed and they marched towards Cawnpore and crossed over the river. While on the march, however, our party was surprised by a troop of mounted sahibs[19] It was early morning, just before the dawn, and we were attacked so suddenly that these brave warriors, so far from attempting to fight and annihilate the Europeans, fled into the jungle. Luckily for me, they forgot to carry out their threat to shoot me. I was pulled out of the pony trap in which I was travelling and narrowly escaped being shot by one of these trooper sahibs who thought I was a wounded or sick sepoy. He had not noticed my chains and could not understand Hindustani. Luckily there was an officer nearby who came up, heard my story, and saw my chains, which were very convincing proof of my story. He gave orders for my chains to be knocked off and took me to the officer commanding who wrote down my statement, my name, and my regiment. He was also very anxious to learn of the conditions in Oudh, and whether I had seen or heard of any sahibs or ladies in the jungles. The last English officer I had seen was the Deputy Commissioner of -------, who was, when I left, carrying on his work as usual but this was a month ago.

As I was not a very good horseman, the Captain sahib could not turn me into a trooper but when he found out that I could read and write Persian, he made me interpreter for the Troop. He also gave me a certificate of the account of my recapture etc. I went about with this rissalah[20] for about six weeks, during which time it destroyed several bands of mutineers and one day had a hand-to-hand fight with a party of regular cavalry. They fired off their pistols and made off as hard as they could although they were three times the size of our party. Nineteen sowars[21] were killed and twenty-one of the best of the Government's horses were taken. We lost five men killed and seven wounded. After this our Troop returned to Cawnpore, which had been re-taken twice by the English. Through the kindness of my Captain—may the shadow of greatness always surround him—he took me to the officer commanding a Punjab regiment,[22] and I was taken on the strength of this corps as a supernumerary Jemadar and attached to it. This regiment was engaged in several actions, and also before Lucknow. We pursued the mutineers right into Nepal and I passed the old place again where I had been so frightened by the elephants forty years previously. All this is so well known that I need not tell it again, but in no fight that I was in—and they were not a few—did I ever see the mutineers, be they Hindus or be they Mahommedans, ever make a good stand and fight. Usually they stood the first discharge and then took to flight—if they could not find shelter behind walls or trees. I am told it was tough work at Delhi. I was not there, but the sepoys could not have fought well to have allowed an English force of under 10,000 defeat 70,000, with the latter in possession of all the houses and fortifications.

One day, in one of the enclosed buildings near Lucknow, a great number of prisoners were taken. These were nearly all sepoys. They were all brought in after the fight to the officer commanding my regiment, and in the morning the order came that they were all to be shot. It happened that it was my turn to command the firing party. I asked the prisoners their names and their regiments. After hearing some five or six, one sepoy said he belonged to a certain regiment which was my son's. I naturally inquired whether he had known my son, Ananti Ram, of the Light Company. He answered that that was his own name. However this is a very common name, and because I had always imagined that my son must have died from the Sind fever, since I had never heard from him, it did not at first strike me. But when he told me that he came from Tilowee, my heart leapt in my mouth. Could he be my long lost son? There was no doubt about it, for he gave my name as his father, and fell down at my feet imploring my pardon. He had mutinied with the rest of his regiment and gone to Lucknow. Once the deed had been done, what else could he do? Where could he have gone, even if he had wanted to escape?

The prisoners were to be shot at four o'clock in the afternoon and I must be my son's executioner! Such is fate! I went to the Major sahib and requested that I might be relieved of this duty as a very great favour. He was very angry and said he would bring me before a court-martial for trying to shirk my duty. He would not believe I was a faithful servant of the English Government—he thought my real sympathies were with the mutineers—and he would not listen to me any further. At last my feelings as a father got the better of me and I burst into floods of tears. I told him that I would shoot every one of the prisoners with my own hands if he ordered me but I confessed that one of them was my own son. The Major declared that I was only making up an excuse to avoid having to shoot my own brethren but at last his heart seemed to be touched. He ordered my unfortunate son to be brought before him and questioned him very strictly.

I shall never forget this terrible scene. Not for one moment did I consider requesting that his life should be spared—that he did not deserve. Eventually the Major came to believe in the truth of my statement and ordered me to be relieved from this duty. I went to my tent bowed down with grief which was made worse by the gibes and taunts of the Sikhs[23] who declared I was a renegade. In a short time I heard a volley. My son had received the reward for mutiny! He showed no fear but I would much rather that he had been killed in battle. Through the kindness of the Major I was allowed to perform the funeral rites over my misguided son. He was the only one of the prisoners over whom it was performed, for the remainder were all thrown to the jackals and the vultures.[24]

I had not heard from my son since just after my return

from slavery. I had not seen him since I went to Kabul, and thus I met him again, untrue to his salt, and in open rebellion against the master who had fed his father and himself. But I have said enough—more is unnecessary. He was not the only soldier who mutinied. The Major told me later that he was much blamed by the other officers for allowing the funeral rites to be performed on a rebel but if good deeds wipe away sins, and I believe some sahibs believe this as we do, then his sins will be very white. Bad luck never waits upon the merciful! May my Major[25] soon become a General.

1. Sita Ram is incorrect. Two battalions of Sikhs were raised in 1846 from those Sikhs living to the east of the Sutlej in British-controlled territory. The 14th Sikhs (Regiment of Ferozepore) subsequently became the 1st (King George V's) Battalion, 11th Sikh Regiment. The 15th Sikhs (Regiment of Ludhiana) became the 2nd (Royal) Battalion, 11th Sikh Regiment. They are today the 1st and 2nd battalions of the Sikh Regiment, Indian Army.

2. Sita Ram refers here to two events which caused great dissatisfaction in the army. The first was the withdrawal of field, or foreign service, allowance for all troops stationed in the Punjab after its annexation in 1849. Mutiny occurred in several regiments, and particularly in the 66th BNI stationed in Amritsar. This regiment was disbanded forthwith by the Commander-in-Chief, Sir Charles Napier, without waiting for the Government's sanction, and its place in the Bengal Native Army was taken by the Nasseri Gurkha battalion, which later became the senior Gurkha regiment in the Indian Army. The other event to which Sita Ram refers is probably the annexation of Oudh by Lord Dalhousie in 1856, as a result of the misgovernment of the King, or Nawab, of Oudh. This led to the sepoys losing their privileged position as soldiers of the Company in the Civil Courts, and was most unpopular. Moreover the disappearance of one of the last independent dynasties of India undoubtedly offended Indian sentiment.

3. The Santhals were aboriginal tribesmen. They lived in the jungle-covered hills of the Santhal Parganas in Bengal and rose in revolt in 1855.

4. Government House, Calcutta.

5. Sita Ram is presumably referring to the junior officials of the Company's Civil Service who were sent to Oudh straight from their training in Calcutta.

6. The hereditary land revenue receivers of Oudh who had become the landed gentry.

7. Misgovernment in Oudh had been notorious for more than fifty years, but each Governor-General in succession had been chary of annexing Oudh. Even Dalhousie had advised that the best solution would be to leave the Nawab as titular ruler, and for the Company to administer Oudh in his name, but the India Board in London chose his alternative solution, which was outright annexation.

8. The Brown Bess had been superseded by the Enfield rifle in 1856. Prior to loading the new rifle it was necessary to bite off the end of the cartridge.

9. The cow is of course sacred to the Hindu, while the pig is unclean to the Mahommedan. The authorities could hardly have chosen a worse preservative for their cartridges than a mixture of cow's fat and lard, which, according to Field-Marshal Lord Roberts, were the ingredients used.

10. Furlough, or long leave, was taken to coincide whenever possible with the harvest.

11. Dissatisfaction among the sepoys of the Bengal Native Army was not new; indeed, it had been gathering strength over a period of thirty years. The surprising thing is that so many British officers seem to have been blind to the discontent.

12. Eighty-five men of the 3rd Bengal Light Cavalry, stationed at Meerut, had refused to receive the offending cartridges. They were tried by court martial on 8 May 1857, publicly degraded by being stripped of their uniform and fettered in front of the entire garrison, and handed over to the civil authorities in the local jail. Two days later, on 10 May, the 3rd Cavalry broke into open mutiny, and were joined by the two Native infantry regiments in the garrison. They released the prisoners and set off for Delhi where they proclaimed Bahadur Shah Emperor of Hindustan, and where they were joined in mutiny by the Delhi garrison. The British regiments stationed at Meerut failed to prevent the mutiny, and the local commanders were woefully dilatory in following up the mutineers on the way to Delhi.

13. Chaprassi: office messenger who waits on the verandah of his master.

14. Sita Ram is of course referring to his own country, Oudh, or what is now the UP. The mutiny was almost entirely confined to the Bengal Native Army. The Madras Army was unaffected, and there was little disaffection in the Bombay Army, despite the fact that many of its sepoys were recruited from Oudh.

15. Holi is one of the principal Hindu festivals and takes place in the spring. It is a kind of Hindu saturnalia, connected with the god Krishna, but must originally have been a fertility ceremony. Few things are barred during Holi and most sober-minded citizens remain indoors; those who venture out must bear their indignities with composure, if not with a smile.

16. There was an almost obsessive belief that the British intended to convert the population to Christianity, and the activities of missionaries in India added fuel to the flames. Moreover this was the period of the evangelical revival in Britain, and men like Havelock and Nicholson, whose religion was a burning faith, merely added to the confusion in the minds of the sepoys.

17. In the Crimean War

18. Dandu Pant, or the Nana Sahib, was the adopted son of the last Peshwa of Poona, head of the Mahratta confederacy. He inherited a vast fortune in 1851, but the pension paid by the Company lapsed on the Peshwa's death. This rankled with the Nana Sahib, and although outwardly friendly to the English, he was in fact thoroughly disgruntled and disloyal. He played a leading part in the Massacre at Cawnpore, his estates being in the vicinity, and became one of the principal villains of the piece so far as the British were concerned. He was never captured and his exact end remains one of the mysteries of the Mutiny.

19. In the confusion following the outbreak of the Mutiny, individual Europeans banded themselves together as Moss-Troopers, such as Vincent Eyre's troop of twelve hog-spears. Indigo planters without plantations, Judges without courts, Officers without regiments, and District Commissioners without districts took to the sword and saddle. They did good work in restoring order in outlying districts but the justice they meted out was sometimes rough and ready. Sita Ram probably joined the Troop of Lousada Barrow of the Madras Cavalry.

20. Rissalah: a Troop of Horse, or Cavalry.

21. Sowar: a horseman, or cavalry trooper.

22. This may have been the 12th Punjab Infantry, which was commanded by Major T. C. Blagrove. The second-in-command was Captain J. T. Norgate, who later commanded the regiment.

23. Sita Ram's antipathy for the Sikhs was shared by many of the old-style British officers. 'I recollect,' says Lord Roberts, 'the commanding officer of the 25th BNI, who had served all his life with clean-looking, closely-shaven Hindustanis, pointing with a look of contempt, not to say disgust, to some Sikhs, and expressing his regret that he could not get them to shave their beards and cut their hair. "They quite spoil the look of my regiment," he said.'

24. The correct performance of the funeral ceremonies is of immense importance for all Hindus, and particularly for Brahmins.

25. It is more than likely that this 'merciful Major' was Norgate, translator of Sita Ram's memoirs. It is known that Sita Ram served under him during the Mutiny, and an incident such as the one described would have formed a strong bond between the two men, and may have accounted for Norgate's success in persuading Sita Ram to part with his memoirs.

Acknowledgements

I must begin by expressing my thanks to my collaborator, Frank Wilson, who has illustrated this book. It is largely as a result of his enthusiasm and encouragement that I have undertaken the editing of these memoirs. He has the advantage over me, having served in the pre-1947 Indian Army, but together we share a deep affection for India and a profound admiration for that splendid fighting man, the Indian soldier.

I have received much assistance from Mr D. W. King and the Staff of the Ministry of Defence Library, the Librarian and Staff of the Royal United Service Institution, and also from Mrs Archer of the India Office Library, Foreign and Commonwealth Office, and Mr W. Y. Carman. I am most grateful to them.

When first I checked through the manuscript to obtain the exact English rendering of the many words in Hindi, I was greatly helped by Captain H. I. S. Kanwar of New Delhi, himself a keen military historian. Major-General K. C. Khanna, Indian Army (retired), a friend of many years’ standing, has also assisted me. I am grateful to them both.

I have also to thank Corporal William Davis, RAF, who has spent long hours typing the manuscript, and whose assistance has been invaluable.

This has really been a labour of love, whatever its shortcomings, and I was fortunate in being able to start the writing of it while serving on the staff of the British High Commissioner in India in 1968. My main acknowledgement must therefore be to India, that fascinating land, and to my many Indian friends who made me feel so welcome wherever I went.